<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://www.gutenberg.org/tei/marcello/0.4/dtd/pgtei.dtd" [

<!ENTITY u5  "http://www.tei-c.org/Lite/">

]>

<TEI.2 lang="en">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>A Source Book for Ancient Church History</title>
      <author><name reg="Ayer, Joseph Cullen">Joseph Cullen Ayer, Jr., Ph.D.</name></author>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition n="1">Edition 1</edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Project Gutenberg</publisher>
      <date>April 2, 2008</date>
      <idno type="etext-no">24979</idno>
      <availability>
        <p>This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and
        with almost no restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it
        away or re-use it under the terms of the Project Gutenberg
        License online at www.gutenberg.org/license</p>
      </availability>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>
        Created electronically.
      </bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language id="en"></language>
      <language id="el"></language>
      <language id="la"></language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change>
      <date value="2008-04-02">April 2,  2008</date>
      <respStmt>
        <name>
            Produced by Greg Weeks, La Monte H.P. Yarrol, David King, and the Online Distributed Proofreading
            Team at &lt;http://www.pgdp.net/&gt;.
            Page-images available at
            &lt;http://www.pgdp.net/projects/projectID4484cbcb67673/&gt;
        </name>
      </respStmt>
      <item>Project Gutenberg TEI edition 1</item>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text lang="en">
  <front>
    <div>
      <divGen type="pgheader" />
    </div>
    <div>
      <divGen type="encodingDesc" />
    </div>

    <div rend="page-break-before: always">
      <p rend="font-size: xx-large; text-align: center; bold">A Source Book for Ancient Church History</p>
      <p rend="font-size: x-large; text-align: center; bold">From the Apostolic Age to the Close of the Conciliar Period</p>
      <p rend="font-size: xx-large; text-align: center; bold">by Joseph Cullen Ayer, Jr., Ph.D.</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">Professor of Ecclesiastical History in the Divinity School of the Protestant Episcopal Church in Philadelphia</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">New York</p>
      <p rend="font-size: large; text-align: center">Charles Scribner's Sons</p>
      <p rend="text-align: center">1913</p>
    </div>
    <div rend="page-break-before: always">
      <head>Contents</head>
      <divGen type="toc" />
    </div>
  </front>

<body>

<pb n='v'/><anchor id='Pgv'/>

<pb n='vii'/><anchor id='Pgvii'/>

<div rend="page-break-before: always">
<index index="toc"/>
<index index="pdf"/>
<head>Preface.</head>

<p>
The value of the source-book has long been recognized in
the teaching of general history. In ecclesiastical history
quite as much use can be made of the same aid in instruction.
It is hoped that the present book may supply a want
increasingly felt by teachers employing modern methods in
teaching ecclesiastical history. It has grown out of classroom
work, and is addressed primarily to those who are
teaching and studying the history of the Christian Church in
universities and seminaries. But it is hoped that it may
serve the constantly increasing number interested in the
early history of Christianity.
</p>

<p>
In the arrangement of the selected illustrative material, a
chronological analysis and grouping of topics has been followed,
according to the lines of treatment employed by K.
Müller, F. Loofs, Von Schubert in his edition of Moeller's
text-book, and by Hergenröther to some extent. The whole
history of ancient Christianity has accordingly been divided
into comparatively brief periods and subdivided into chapters
and sections. These divisions are connected and introduced
by brief analyses and characterizations, with some indications
of additional source material available in English.
</p>

<p>
A bibliography originally prepared for each chapter and
section has been omitted. When the practical question arose
of either reducing the amount of source material to admit a
bibliography, or of making the book too expensive for general
use by students, the main purpose of the book determined the
only way of avoiding two unsatisfactory solutions of the problem,
and the bibliography has been omitted. In this there
may be less loss than at first appears. The student of ecclesiastical
<pb n='viii'/><anchor id='Pgviii'/>
history is fortunately provided with ample bibliographical
material for the ancient Church in the universally
available theological and other encyclopædias which have
very recently appeared or are in course of publication, and in
the recent works on patristics. Possibly the time has come
when, in place of duplicating bibliographies, reliance in such
matters upon the work of others may not be regarded as
mortal sin against the ethics of scholarship. A list of works
has been given in the General Bibliographical Note, which the
student is expected to consult and to which the instructor
should encourage him to go for further information and bibliographical
material.
</p>

<p>
The book presupposes the use of a text-book of Church
history, such as those by Cheetham, Kurtz, Moeller, Funk, or
Duchesne, and a history of doctrine, such as those of Seeberg,
Bethune-Baker, Fisher, or Tixeront. Readings in more elaborate
treatises, special monographs, and secular history may
well be left to the direction of the instructor.
</p>

<p>
The translations, with a few exceptions which are noted,
are referred for the sake of convenience to the <hi rend='italic'>Patrology</hi> of
Migne or Mansi's <hi rend='italic'>Concilia</hi>. Although use has been freely
made of the aid offered by existing translations, especially
those of the <hi rend='italic'>Ante-Nicene</hi> and
<hi rend='italic'>Post-Nicene Fathers</hi>, yet all translations
have been revised in accordance with the best critical
texts available. The aim in the revision has been accuracy
and closeness to the original without too gross violation of the
English idiom, and with exactness in the rendering of ecclesiastical
and theological technical terms. Originality is hardly
to be expected in such a work as this.
</p>

<p>
An author may not be conscious of any attempt to make
his selection of texts illustrate or support any particular phase
of Christian belief or ecclesiastical polity, and his one aim may
be to treat the matter objectively and to render his book
useful to all, yet he ought not to flatter himself that in either
respect he has been entirely successful. In ecclesiastical
history, no more than in any other branch of history, is it
<pb n='ix'/><anchor id='Pgix'/>
possible for an author who is really absorbed in his work to
eliminate completely the personal equation. He should be
glad to be informed of any instance in which he may have
unwittingly failed in impartiality, that when occasion presented
he might correct it. The day has gone by in which
ecclesiastical history can not be treated save as a branch of
polemical theology or as an apologetic for any particular
phase of Christian belief or practice. It has at last become
possible to teach the history of the Christian Church, for many
centuries the greatest institution of Western Europe, in colleges
and universities in conjunction with other historical courses.
</p>

<p>
This volume has been prepared at the suggestion of the
American Society of Church History, and valuable suggestions
have been gained from the discussions of that society. To
Professor W. W. Rockwell, of Union Theological Seminary,
New York, Professor F. A. Christie, of Meadville Theological
School, the late Professor Samuel Macauley Jackson, of New
York, and Professor Ephraim Emerton, of Harvard University,
I have also been indebted for advice. The first two
named were members with me of a committee on a <hi rend='italic'>Source-Book
for Church History</hi> appointed several years ago by the
American Society of Church History.
</p>

<p>
That the book now presented to the public may be of service
to the teacher and student of ecclesiastical history is my
sincere wish. It may easily happen that no one else would
make just the same selection of sources here made. But it
is probable that the principal documents, those on which the
majority would agree and which are most needed by the
teacher in his work, are included among those presented.
There are, no doubt, slips and defects in a book written at
intervals in a teacher's work. With the kind co-operation of
those who detect them, they may be corrected when an opportunity
occurs.
</p>

<ab>
<hi rend="font-variant: small-caps">Joseph Cullen Ayer, Jr.</hi>
</ab>

</div>

<pb n='xix'/><anchor id='Pgxix'/>

<div rend="page-break-before: always">
<index index="toc"/>
<index index="pdf"/>
<head>General Bibliographical Note</head>

<p>
Under each period special collections of available sources are to be
found. The student is not given any bibliography of works bearing
on the topics, but is referred to the following accessible works of
reference of recent date for additional information and bibliographies:
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>The New Schaff-Herzog Encyclopædia of Religious Knowledge</hi>, edited
by S. M. Jackson, New York, 1908-12.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>The Catholic Encyclopædia</hi>, New York, 1907-12.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>The Encyclopædia Britannica</hi>, eleventh edition, Cambridge, 1910.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>The Encyclopædia of Religion and Ethics</hi>, edited by J. Hastings,
Edinburgh and New York, 1908 ff. (In course of publication.)
</p>

<p>
For the patristic writers, their lives, works, editions, and other bibliographical
matter, see:
</p>

<p>
G. Krüger, <hi rend='italic'>History of Early Christian Literature in the First Three
Centuries</hi>, English translation by C. R. Gillett, New York, 1897.
Cited as Krüger.
</p>

<p>
B. Bardenhewer, <hi rend='italic'>Patrologie</hi>, Freiburg-i.-B., 1911, English
translation of second edition (1901) by T. J. Shahan, St. Louis, 1908. Cited
as Bardenhewer.
</p>

<p>
In addition to the encyclopædias the following are indispensable,
and should be consulted:
</p>

<p>
Smith and Wace, <hi rend='italic'>Dictionary of Christian Biography</hi>, Literature,
Sects and Doctrines, London, 1877-87. (The Condensed Edition of
1911 by no means takes the place of this standard work.) Cited
DCB.
</p>

<p>
Smith and Cheetham, <hi rend='italic'>Dictionary of Christian Antiquities</hi>, London,
1875-80. Cited DCA.
</p>

<pb n='xx'/><anchor id='Pgxx'/>

<p>
Advanced students and those capable of using French and German
are referred to the following, which have admirable and authoritative
articles and ample bibliographies:
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Realencyclopædie für protestantische Theologie</hi>, edited by A.
Hauck, Leipsic, 1896 <hi rend='italic'>ff.</hi> Two supplementary volumes appeared in
1913. Cited PRE.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Kirchenlexicon oder Encyclopædie der katholischen Theologie und ihrer
Hilfswissenschaften</hi>, second edition, by J. Hergenröther und F.
Kaulen, Freiburg-i.-B., 1882-1901. Cited KL.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Dictionnaire de Théologie Catholique</hi>, edited by A. Vacant and E.
Mangenot, Paris, 1903 <hi rend='italic'>ff.</hi>
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Dictionnaire d'Archéologie Chrétienne et de Liturgie</hi>, edited by
F. Cabrol, 1903 <hi rend='italic'>ff.</hi>
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>Dictionnaire d'Histoire et de Géographie Ecclesiastiques</hi>; edited
by A. Baudrillart, A. Vogt, and U. Roziès, Paris, 1909 <hi rend='italic'>ff.</hi>
</p>

<p>
Collections of sources in the original languages, easily procured
and to be consulted for texts and to some extent for bibliographies:
</p>

<p>
C. Mirbt, <hi rend='italic'>Quellen zur Geschichte des Papsttums und des römischen
Katholizismus</hi>, third edition, Tübingen, 1911. Cited as Mirbt.
</p>

<p>
C. Kirch, S. J., <hi rend='italic'>Enchiridion fontium historiæ ecclesiasticæ
antiquæ</hi>. Freiburg-i.-B., 1910. Cited as Kirch.
</p>

<p>
H. Denziger, <hi rend='italic'>Enchiridion symbolorum, definitionum et declarationum de
rebus fidei et morum</hi>, eleventh edition, edited by Clemens Bannwart,
S. J., Freiburg-i.-B., 1911. Cited as Denziger.
</p>

<p>
A. Hahn. <hi rend='italic'>Bibliothek der Symbole und Glaubensregeln der alten
Kirche</hi>, third edition, Breslau, 1897. Cited as Hahn.
</p>

<p>
G. Krüger. <hi rend='italic'>Sammlung ausgewählter kirchen und dogmengeschichtlicher
Quellenschriften</hi>, Freiburg-i.-B.
</p>

<p>
Of this useful collection especially important are the following
of more general application:
</p>

<p>
E. Preuschen, <hi rend='italic'>Analecta: Kürzere Texte zur Geschichte der alten
Kirche und des Kanons</hi>, second edition, 1909-10.
</p>

<p>
F. Lauchert, <hi rend='italic'>Die Kanones der wichtigsten altkirchlichen Concilien
nebst den apostolischen Kanones</hi>.
</p>

<p>
R. Knopf, <hi rend='italic'>Ausgewählte Märtyreracten</hi>. Cited as Knopf.
</p>

<p>
Other volumes are cited in connection with topics.
</p>

<pb n='xxi'/><anchor id='Pgxxi'/>

<p>
H. T. Bruns, <hi rend='italic'>Canones apostolorum et conciliorum sæculorum IV, V, VI,
VII</hi>, Berlin, 1839. Cited as Bruns.
</p>

<p>
Although not source-books, yet of very great value for the sources
they contain should be mentioned:
</p>

<p>
J. C. L. Gieseler, <hi rend='italic'>A Text-Book of Church History</hi>, English
translation, New York, 1857.
</p>

<p>
K. R. Hagenbach, <hi rend='italic'>A History of Christian Doctrines</hi>, English
translation, Edinburgh, 1883-85.
</p>

<p>
C. J. Hefele, <hi rend='italic'>Conciliengeschichte</hi>, Freiburg-i.-B., 1855-70. Second
edition, 1873 <hi rend='italic'>et seq.</hi> A new French translation with admirable
supplementary notes has just appeared. The English translation
(<hi rend='italic'>History of the Councils</hi>), Edinburgh, 1876-95, extends only
through the eighth century. Cited as Hefele.
</p>

</div>

<pb n='003'/><anchor id='Pg003'/>

<div rend="page-break-before: always">
<index index="toc"/>
<index index="pdf"/>
<head>The First Division Of Ancient Christianity: The Church Under The Heathen Empire: To A. D. 324</head>

<p>
By the accession of Constantine to the sole sovereignty of
the Roman Empire, A. D. 324, ancient Christianity may be
conveniently divided into two great periods. In the first, it
was a religion liable to persecution, suffering severely at
times and always struggling to maintain itself; in the second,
it became the religion of the State, and in its turn set about
to repress and persecute the heathen religions. It was no
longer without legal rights; it had the support of the secular
rulers and was lavishly endowed with wealth. The conditions
of the Church in these two periods are so markedly different,
and the conditions had such a distinct effect upon the
life and growth of the Christian religion, that the reign of
Constantine is universally recognized as marking a transition
from one historical period to another, although no date which
shall mark that transition is universally accepted. The year
311, the year in which the Diocletian persecution ceased, has
been accepted by many as the dividing point. The exact
date adopted is immaterial.
</p>

<p>
The principal sources in English for the history of the
Christian Church before A. D. 324 are:
</p>

<p>
<hi rend='italic'>The Ante-Nicene Fathers. Translations of the Writings of
the Fathers down to A. D. 325.</hi> American edition, Buffalo
and New York, 1885-1896; new edition, New York, 1896 (a
reprint). The collection, cited as ANF, contains the bulk of
<pb n='004'/><anchor id='Pg004'/>
the Christian literature of the period, with the exception of
the less important commentaries of Origen.
</p>

<p>
Eusebius, <hi rend='italic'>Church History</hi>. Translated with Prolegomena
and Notes by Arthur Cushman McGiffert. In <hi rend='italic'>A Select Library
of the Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers of the Christian Church</hi>.
Second series, New York, 1890. The <hi rend='italic'>Church History</hi> of
Eusebius is the foundation of the study of the history of the
Church before A. D. 324, as it contains a vast number of citations
from works now lost. The edition by Professor McGiffert
is the best in English, and is provided with scholarly
notes, which serve as an elaborate commentary on the text.
It should be in every library. This work is cited as Eusebius,
<hi rend='italic'>Hist. Ec.</hi> The text used in the extracts given in this source
book is that of Ed. Schwartz, in <hi rend='italic'>Die Griechischen Christlicher:
Schriftsteller der ersten drei Jahrhunderte</hi>. Kleine Ausgabe,
Leipsic, 1908. This text is identical with the larger and less
convenient edition by the same editor.
</p>

<pb n='005'/><anchor id='Pg005'/>

<div rend="page-break-before: always">
<index index="toc"/>
<index index="pdf"/>
<head>Period I. The Apostolic Age: To Circa A. D. 100</head>

<p>
The period in the Church before the clash with Gnosticism
and the rise of an apologetic literature comprises the apostolic
and the post-apostolic ages. These names have become traditional.
The so-called apostolic age, or to circa 100, is that
in which the Apostles lived, though the best tradition makes
John the only surviving Apostle for the last quarter of a
century.
</p>

<p>
The principal sources for the history of the Church in this
period are the books of the New Testament, and only to a
slight degree the works of contemporaneous Jewish and
heathen writers. It is hardly necessary to reproduce New
Testament passages here. The Jewish references of importance
will be found in the works on the life of Christ and of
St. Paul. As the treatment of this period commonly falls
under a different branch of study, New Testament exegesis,
it is not necessary in Church history to enter into any detail.
There are, however, a few references to events in this period
which are to be found only outside the New Testament, and
are of importance to the student of Church history. These
are the Neronian persecution (§ 1), the death of the Apostles
(§§ 2, 3), and the persecution under Domitian (§ 4). The
paucity of references to Christianity in the first century is
due chiefly to the fact that Christianity appeared to the men
of the times as merely a very small Oriental religion, struggling
for recognition, and contending with many others coming
from the same region. It had not yet made any great advance
either in numbers or social importance.
</p>

<pb n='006'/><anchor id='Pg006'/>

<div>
<index index="toc"/>
<index index="pdf"/>
<anchor id="Section_1"/>
<head>§ 1. The Neronian Persecution</head>

<p>
The Neronian persecution took place A. D. 64. The occasion
was the great fire which destroyed a large part of the
city of Rome. To turn public suspicion from himself as responsible
for the fire, Nero attempted to make the Christians
appear as the incendiaries. Many were put to death in horrible
and fantastic ways. It was not, however, a persecution
directed against Christianity as an unlawful religion. It was
probably confined to Rome and at most the immediate vicinity,
and there is no evidence that it was a general persecution.
</p>

<p>
Additional source material: Lactantius, <hi rend='italic'>De Mortibus Persecutorum</hi>,
ch. 2 (ANF, VII); Sulpicius Severus, Chronicon, II. 28 (PNF, ser. II,
vol. XI).
</p>

<div>
<head>(<hi rend='italic'>a</hi>) Tacitus, <hi rend='italic'>Annales</hi>, XV, 44.
Preuschen, <hi rend='italic'>Analecta</hi>, I, § 3:1. Mirbt, n. 3.</head>

<quote rend="display">
Tacitus (c. 52-c. 117), although not an eye-witness of the persecution,
had exceptionally good opportunities for obtaining accurate information,
and his account is entirely trustworthy. He is the principal
source for the persecution.
</quote>

<p>
Neither by works of benevolence nor the gifts of the prince
nor means of appeasing the gods did the shameful suspicion
cease, so that it was not believed that the fire had been
caused by his command. Therefore, to overcome this rumor,
Nero put in his own place as culprits, and punished with most
ingenious cruelty, men whom the common people hated for
their shameful crimes and called Christians. Christ, from
whom the name was derived, had been put to death in the
reign of Tiberius by the procurator Pontius Pilate. The
deadly superstition, having been checked for a while, began
to break out again, not only throughout Judea, where this
<pb n='007'/><anchor id='Pg007'/>
mischief first arose, but also at Rome, where from all sides all
things scandalous and shameful meet and become fashionable.
Therefore, at the beginning, some were seized who made confessions;
then, on their information, a vast multitude was convicted,
not so much of arson as of hatred of the human race.
And they were not only put to death, but subjected to insults,
in that they were either dressed up in the skins of wild beasts
and perished by the cruel mangling of dogs, or else put on
crosses to be set on fire, and, as day declined, to be burned,
being used as lights by night. Nero had thrown open his
gardens for that spectacle, and gave a circus play, mingling
with the people dressed in a charioteer's costume or driving in
a chariot. From this arose, however, toward men who were,
indeed, criminals and deserving extreme penalties, sympathy,
on the ground that they were destroyed not for the public
good, but to satisfy the cruelty of an individual.
</p>

</div>

<div>
<head>(<hi rend='italic'>b</hi>) Clement of Rome, <hi rend='italic'>Ep. ad
Corinthios</hi>, I, 5, 6. Funk, <hi rend='italic'>Patres Apostolici</hi>, 1901. (MSG,
1:218.) Preuschen, <hi rend='italic'>Analecta</hi>, I, § 3:5.</head>

<quote rend="display">
The work known as the First Epistle of Clement to the Corinthians
was written in the name of the Roman Church about 100. The occasion
was the rise of contentions in the Corinthian Church. The name
of Clement does not appear in the body of the epistle, but there is no
good ground for questioning the traditional ascription to Clement,
since before the end of the second century it was quoted under his name
by several writers. This Clement was probably the third or fourth
bishop of Rome. The epistle was written soon after the Domitian
persecution (A. D. 95), and refers not only to that but also to an earlier
persecution, which was very probably that under Nero. As the reference
is only by way of illustration, the author gives little detail. The
passage translated is of interest as containing the earliest reference
to the death of the Apostles Peter and Paul, and the language used
regarding Paul has been thought to imply that he labored in parts
beyond Rome.
</quote>

<p>
Ch. 5. But to leave the ancient examples, let us come to the
champions who lived nearest our times; let us take the noble
examples of our generation. On account of jealousy and
envy the greatest and most righteous pillars of the Church
<pb n='008'/><anchor id='Pg008'/>
were persecuted, and contended even unto death. Let us set
before our eyes the good Apostles: Peter, who on account of
unrighteous jealousy endured not one nor two, but many
sufferings, and so, having borne his testimony, went to his
deserved place of glory. On account of jealousy and strife
Paul pointed out the prize of endurance. After he had been
seven times in bonds, had been driven into exile, had been
stoned, had been a preacher in the East and in the West, he
received the noble reward of his faith; having taught righteousness
unto the whole world, and having come to the farthest
bounds of the West, and having borne witness before rulers,
he thus departed from the world and went unto the holy
place, having become a notable pattern of patient endurance.
</p>

<p>
Ch. 6. Unto these men who lived lives of holiness was
gathered a vast multitude of the elect, who by many indignities
and tortures, being the victims of jealousy, set the
finest examples among us. On account of jealousy women,
when they had been persecuted as Danaïds and Dircæ, and
had suffered cruel and unholy insults, safely reached the goal
in the race of faith and received a noble reward, feeble though
they were in body.
</p>

</div>

</div>

<div>
<index index="toc"/>
<index index="pdf"/>
<anchor id="Section_2"/>
<head>§ 2. The Death of Peter and Paul</head>

<quote rend="display">
Eusebius, <hi rend='italic'>Hist. Ec.</hi>, II, 25. (MSG, 20:207.)
<hi rend='italic'>Cf.</hi> Mirbt, n. 33.
</quote>

<quote rend="display">
For an examination of the merits of Eusebius as a historian, see
McGiffert's edition, PNF, ser. II, vol. I, pp. 45-52; also J. B. Lightfoot,
art. <q>Eusebius (23) of Caesarea,</q> in DCB.
</quote>

<quote rend="display">
The works of Caius have been preserved only in fragments; see
Krüger, § 90. If he was a contemporary of Zephyrinus, he probably
lived during the pontificate of that bishop of Rome, 199-217 A. D.
The Phrygian heresy which Caius combated was Montanism; see
below, <ref target="Section_25">§ 25</ref>.
</quote>

<quote rend="display">
Dionysius, Bishop of Corinth, was a contemporary of Soter, Bishop
of Rome, 166-174 A. D., whom he mentions in an epistle to the Roman
Church. Of his epistles only fragments have been preserved; see
Krüger, § 55. The following extract from his epistle to the Roman
Church is the earliest explicit statement that Peter and Paul suffered
<pb n='009'/><anchor id='Pg009'/>
martyrdom at the same time or that Peter was ever in Italy. In connection
with this extract, that from Clement of Rome (see § 1, <hi rend='italic'>a</hi>) should
be consulted; also Lactantius, <hi rend='italic'>De Mortibus Persecutorum</hi>, ch. 2
(ANF).
</quote>

<p>
It is therefore recorded that Paul was beheaded at Rome
itself, and that Peter was crucified likewise at the same time.
This account of Peter and Paul is confirmed by the fact that
their names are preserved in the cemeteries of that place even
to the present time. It is confirmed no less by a member of
the Church, Caius by name, a contemporary of Zephyrinus,
Bishop of Rome. In carrying on a discussion in writing with
Proclus, the leader of the Phrygian heresy, he says as follows
concerning the places where the sacred corpses of the aforesaid
Apostles are laid: <q>But I am able to show the trophies
of the Apostles. For if you will go to the Vatican or to the
Ostian Way, you will find the trophies of those who laid the
foundations of this church.</q> And that they two suffered
martyrdom at the same time is stated by Dionysius, Bishop
of Corinth, corresponding with the Romans in writing, in
the following words: <q>You have thus by such admonition
bound together the planting of Peter and Paul at Rome and
at Corinth. For both planted in our Corinth and likewise
taught us, and in like manner in Italy they both taught and
suffered martyrdom at the same time.</q>
</p>

</div>

<div>
<index index="toc"/>
<index index="pdf"/>
<anchor id="Section_3"/>
<head>§ 3. The Death of the Apostle John</head>

<div>
<anchor id="Section_3_a"/>
<head>(<hi rend='italic'>a</hi>) Irenæus, <hi rend='italic'>Adversus Hæreses</hi>, II,
22, 5; III, 3, 4. (MSG, 7:785, 854.)</head>

<quote rend="display">
Irenæus was bishop of Lyons soon after 177. He was born in Asia
Minor about 120, and was a disciple of Polycarp (ob. circa 155) and
of other elders who had seen John, the disciple of the Lord.
</quote>

<p>
II, 22, 5. Those in Asia associated with John, the disciple
of the Lord, testify that John delivered it [a tradition regarding
the length of Christ's ministry] to them. For he remained
among them until the time of Trajan [98-117 A. D.].
</p>

<p>
III, 3, 4. But the church in Ephesus also, which was
<pb n='010'/><anchor id='Pg010'/>
founded by Paul, and where John remained until the time of
Trajan, is a faithful witness of the apostolic tradition.
</p>

</div>

<div>
<head>(<hi rend='italic'>b</hi>) Jerome, <hi rend='italic'>Comm. ad Galat.</hi> (MSL,
26:462.)</head>

<quote rend="display">
The following extract from Jerome's commentary on Galatians is
of such late date as to be of doubtful value as an authority. There is,
however, nothing improbable in it, and it is in harmony with other
traditions. It is to be taken as a tradition which at any rate represents
the opinion of the fourth century regarding the Apostle John.
<hi rend='italic'>Cf.</hi> Jerome, <hi rend='italic'>De Viris Inlustribus</hi>,
ch. 9 (PNF, ser. II, vol. III, 364).
</quote>

<p>
When the holy Evangelist John had lived to extreme old
age in Ephesus, he could be carried only with difficulty by the
hands of the disciples, and as he was not able to pronounce
more words, he was accustomed to say at every assembly,
<q>Little children, love one another.</q> At length the disciples
and brethren who were present became tired of hearing always
the same thing and said: <q>Master, why do you always say
this?</q> Thereupon John gave an answer worthy of himself:
<q>Because this is the commandment of the Lord, and if it is
observed then is it enough.</q>
</p>

</div>

<div>
<head>(<hi rend='italic'>c</hi>) Eusebius, <hi rend='italic'>Hist. Ec.</hi>, III, 31.
(MSG, 20:279.)</head>

<quote rend="display">
Polycrates was bishop of Ephesus and a contemporary of Victor of
Rome (189-199 A. D.). His date cannot be fixed more precisely.
The reference to the <q>high priest's mitre</q> is obscure; see J. B. Lightfoot,
<hi rend='italic'>Commentary on the Epistle to the Galatians</hi>, p. 345.
A longer extract
from this epistle of Polycrates will be found under the Easter
Controversy (<ref target="Section_38">§ 38</ref>).
</quote>

<p>
The time of John's death has been given in a general way,<note place="foot">See
Eusebius, <hi rend='italic'>Hist. Ec.</hi>, III, 23, who gives quotations from
Irenæus. This passage also gives a lengthy extract from the work of Clement of
Alexandria, <hi rend='italic'>Quis dives salvetur</hi>, bearing on St. John's
life at Ephesus (ANF. II, 591-604).</note>
but his burial-place is indicated by an epistle of Polycrates
(who was bishop of the parish of Ephesus) addressed to Victor
of Rome, mentioning him, together with the Apostle Philip
and his daughters, in the following words: <q>For in Asia also
great lights have fallen asleep, which shall rise again at the
last day, at the coming of the Lord, when he shall come with
<pb n='011'/><anchor id='Pg011'/>
glory from heaven and seek out all the saints. Among these
are Philip, one of the twelve Apostles, who sleeps at Hierapolis,
and his two aged virgin daughters, and another daughter who
lived in the Holy Spirit and now rests at Ephesus; and moreover
John, who was both a witness and a teacher, who reclined
upon the bosom of the Lord, and being a priest wore
the high priest's mitre, also sleeps at Ephesus.</q>
</p>

</div>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
