<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://www.gutenberg.org/tei/marcello/0.4/dtd/pgtei.dtd">
<TEI.2 lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Rambles and Studies in Greece</title>
                <author><name reg="Mahaffy, J. P.">J. P. Mahaffy</name></author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Project Gutenberg</publisher>
                <date value="2011-02-16">February 16, 2011</date>
                <idno type='etext-no'>35298</idno>
                <availability>
                  <p>This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere
                  at no cost and with almost no restrictions whatsoever.
                  You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under
                  the terms of the Project Gutenberg License online at
                  www.gutenberg.org/license</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><author><name reg="Mahaffy, J. P.">J. P. Mahaffy</name></author>
                <title>Rambles and Studies in Greece</title>
                    <imprint><pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Henry T. Coates &amp; Co.</publisher>
                    <date>1900</date></imprint>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
          <langUsage>
            <language id="fr" />
            <language id="en" />
              <language id="el"/>
          </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
          <change>
            <date value="2011-02-16">February 16, 2011</date>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Produced by <name>Juliet Sutherland</name>,
                    <name>Stefan Cramme</name>, and the Online Distributed Proofreading Team
                    at http://www.pgdp.net</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Project Gutenberg TEI edition 1</item>
          </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text lang="en">
<front>
    <div>
      <divGen type="pgheader" />
    </div>
    <div>
      <divGen type="encodingDesc" />
    </div>
    <div rend="page-break-before: always">
    <figure url="images/cover.png" rend="w80"><figDesc>Cover image</figDesc></figure>
<pb/><anchor id='Pgi'/>

<p rend="text-align: center; page-break-before:always; font-size:large">RAMBLES IN GREECE</p>

<pb/><anchor id='Pgii'/>
<anchor id="frontis"/><index index="fig" level1="The Acropolis, Athens"/>
<pgIf output='txt'><then>
  <p rend="ill">[Illustration: The Acropolis, Athens]</p>
</then><else>
  <p rend="page-break-before:always"><figure url="images/illus001.jpg" rend="w100"><head>The Acropolis, Athens</head><figDesc>The Acropolis, Athens</figDesc></figure></p>
</else></pgIf>
    </div>
    <titlePage rend="text-align: center; page-break-before: always">
<pb/><anchor id='Pgiii'/>

<docTitle>
    <titlePart><hi rend="font-size: x-large">RAMBLES AND STUDIES</hi><lb/><lb/>
    IN<lb/><lb/>
    <hi rend="font-size: xx-large">GREECE</hi></titlePart>
</docTitle>
<lb/><lb/>
<byline>BY
<lb/>
<docAuthor><hi rend="font-size: large">J. P. MAHAFFY</hi></docAuthor>
<lb/>
    <hi rend="font-size: small">KNIGHT OF THE ORDER OF THE SAVIOUR;<lb/>
   AUTHOR OF <q>SOCIAL LIFE IN GREECE;</q> <q>A HISTORY OF GREEK LITERATURE;</q><lb/>
    <q>GREEK LIFE AND THOUGHT FROM THE DEATH OF ALEXANDER;</q><lb/>
    <q>THE GREEK WORLD UNDER ROMAN SWAY,</q> ETC.</hi>
</byline>
    <lb/>
    <titlePart>ILLUSTRATED</titlePart>
  <lb/><lb/>
<docImprint><pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA</pubPlace><lb/>
                    <publisher>HENRY T. COATES &amp; CO.</publisher><lb/>
                    <date>1900</date></docImprint>  
<pb/><anchor id='Pgiv'/>    
</titlePage><div rend="page-break-before: always">
<pb/><anchor id='Pgv'/>
<p rend="text-align: center">
HUNC LIBRUM<lb/>    
  <hi rend='fraktur'>Edmundo Wyatt Edgell</hi><lb/>
    <hi rend="font-size: small">OB INSIGNEM<lb/>
    INTER CASTRA ITINERA OTIA NEGOTIA LITTERARUM AMOREM<lb/>
    OLIM DEDICATUM</hi><lb/>
    NUNC CARISSIMI AMICI MEMORIAE<lb/>
    CONSECRAT AUCTOR
</p>

<pb/><anchor id='Pgvi'/>

</div><div rend="page-break-before: always">
<pb n='vii'/><anchor id='Pgvii'/>
<index index="toc" level1="Preface"/><index index="pdf" level1="Preface"/>
<head>PREFACE.</head>

<p>
Few men there are who having once visited Greece
do not contrive to visit it again. And yet when the
returned traveller meets the ordinary friend who asks
him where he has been, the next remark is generally,
<q>Dear me! have you not been there before? How is
it you are so fond of going to Greece?</q> There are
even people who imagine a trip to America far more
interesting, and who at all events look upon a trip
to Spain as the same kind of thing—southern climate,
bad food, dirty inns, and general discomfort, odious
to bear, though pleasant to describe afterward in a
comfortable English home.
</p>

<p>
This is a very ignorant way of looking at the
matter, for excepting Southern Italy, there is no
country which can compare with Greece in beauty
and interest to the intelligent traveller. It is not
a land for creature comforts, though the climate is
splendid, and though the hotels in Athens are as
good as those in most European towns. It is not a
land for society, though the society at Athens is
excellent, and far easier of access than that of most
European capitals. But if a man is fond of the large
<pb n='viii'/><anchor id='Pgviii'/>effects of natural scenery, he will find in the Southern
Alps and fiords of Greece a variety and a richness
of color which no other part of Europe affords.
If he is fond of the details of natural scenery, flowers,
shrubs, and trees, he will find the wild-flowers and
flowering-trees of Greece more varied than anything
he has yet seen. If he desires to study national
character, and peculiar manners and customs, he
will find in the hardy mountaineers of Greece one of
the most unreformed societies, hardly yet affected by
the great tide of sameness which is invading all
Europe in dress, fabrics, and usages. And yet, in
spite of the folly still talked in England about brigands,
he will find that without troops, or police, or
patrols, or any of those melancholy safeguards which
are now so obtrusive in England and Ireland, life
and property are as secure as they ever were in our
most civilized homes. Let him not know a word of
history, or of art, and he will yet be rewarded by all
this natural enjoyment; perhaps also, if he be a
politician, he may study the unsatisfactory results of
a constitution made to order, and of a system of free
education planted in a nation of no political training,
but of high intelligence.
</p>

<p>
Need I add that as to Cicero the whole land was
one vast shrine of hallowed memories—<hi rend='italic'>quocunque
incedis, historia est</hi>—so to the man of culture this
splendor of associations has only increased with the
lapse of time and the greater appreciation of human
<pb n='ix'/><anchor id='Pgix'/>perfection. Even were such a land dead to all
further change, and a mere record in its ruins of the
past, I know not that any man of reflection could
satisfy himself with contemplating it. Were he to
revisit the Parthenon, as it stands, every year of his
life, it would always be fresh, it would always be
astonishing. But Greece is a growing country, both
in its youth and in its age. The rapid development
of the nation is altering the face of the country,
establishing new roads and better communications,
improving knowledge among the people, and making
many places accessible which were before beyond
the reach of brief holiday visits. The insecurity
which haunted the Turkish frontier has been pushed
back to the north; new Alps and new monasteries
are brought within the range of Greece. And this
is nothing to what has been done in recovering the
past. Every year there are new excavations made,
new treasures found, new problems in archæology
raised, old ones solved; and so at every visit there
is a whole mass of new matter for the student who
feels he had not yet grasped what was already there.
</p>

<p>
The traveller who revisits the country now after
a lapse of four or five years will find at Athens the
Schliemann museum set up and in order, where the
unmatched treasures of Mycenæ are now displayed
before his astonished eyes. He will find an Egyptian
museum of extraordinary merit—the gift of a
patriotic merchant of Alexandria—in which there
<pb n='x'/><anchor id='Pgx'/>are two figures—that of a queen, in bronze and
silver, and that of a slave kneading bread, in wood—which
alone would make the reputation of any
collection throughout Europe. In the Parthenon
museum he will find the famous statuette, copied
from Phidias’s Athene, and the recent wonder,
archaic statues on which the brightness of the colors
is not more astonishing than the moulding of the
figures.
</p>

<p>
And these are only the most salient novelties. It
is indeed plain that were not the new city covering
the site of the old, discoveries at Athens might be
made perhaps every year, which would reform and
enlarge our knowledge of Greek life and history.
</p>

<p>
But Athens is rapidly becoming a great and rich
city. It already numbers 110,000, without counting
the Peiræus; accordingly, except in digging foundations
for new houses, it is not possible to find room
for any serious excavations. House rent is enormously
high, and building is so urgent that the ordinary
mason receives eight to ten francs per day.
This rapid increase ought to be followed by an equal
increase in the wealth of the surrounding country,
where all the little proprietors ought to turn their
land into market-gardens. I found that either they
could not, or (as I was told) they would not, keep
pace with the increased wants of the city. They
are content with a little, and allow the city to be
supplied—badly and at great cost—from Salonica,
<pb n='xi'/><anchor id='Pgxi'/>Syra, Constantinople, and the islands, while meat
comes in tons from America. How different is the
country round Paris and London!
</p>

<p>
But this is a digression into vulgar matters, when
I had merely intended to inform the reader what
intellectual novelties he would find in revisiting
Athens. For nothing is more slavish in modern
travel than the inability the student feels, for want
of time in long journeys, or want of control over his
conveyance, to stop and examine something which
strikes him beside his path. And that is the main
reason why Oriental—and as yet Greek—travelling
is the best and most instructive of all.
</p>

<p>
You can stop your pony or mule, you can turn
aside from the track which is called your road, you
are not compelled to catch a train or a steamer at a
fixed moment. When roads and rails have been
brought into Greece, hundreds of people will go to
see its beauty and its monuments, and will congratulate
themselves that the country is at last accessible.
But the real charm will be gone. There will be no
more riding at dawn through orchards of oranges
and lemons, with the rich fruit lying on the ground,
and the nightingales, that will not end their exuberant
melody, still outsinging from the deep-green
gloom the sounds of opening day. There will be no
more watching the glowing east cross the silver-gray
glitter of dewy meadows; no more wandering along
grassy slopes, where the scarlet anemones, all
<pb n='xii'/><anchor id='Pgxii'/>drenched with the dews of night, are striving to
raise their drooping heads and open their splendid
eyes to meet the rising sun. There will be no more
watching the serpent and the tortoise, the eagle and
the vulture, and all the living things whose ways and
habits animate the sunny solitudes of the south.
The Greek people now talk of going to Europe, and
coming from Europe, justly too, for Greece is still,
as it always was, part of the East. But the day is
coming when enlightened politicians, like Mr. Tricoupi,
will insist on introducing through all the remotest
glens the civilization of Europe, with all its
benefits forsooth, but with all its shocking ugliness,
its stupid hurry, and its slavish uniformity.
</p>

<p>
I will conclude with a warning to the archæologist,
and one which applies to all amateurs who go to visit
excavations, and cannot see what has been reported
by the actual excavators. As no one is able to see
what the evidences of digging are, except the trained
man, who knows not only archæology, but architecture,
and who has studied the accumulation of soil
in various places and forms, so the observer who
comes to the spot after some years, and expects to
find all the evidences unchanged, commits a blunder
of the gravest kind. As Dr. Dörpfeld, now one of
the highest living authorities on such matters, observed
to me, if you went to Hissarlik expecting to
find there clearly marked the various strata of successive
occupations, you would show that you were
<pb n='xiii'/><anchor id='Pgxiii'/>ignorant of the first elements of practical knowledge.
For in any climate, but especially in these southern
lands, Nature covers up promptly what has been
exposed by man; all sorts of plants spring up along
and across the lines which in the cutting when
freshly made were clear and precise. In a few
years the whole place turns back again into a brake,
or a grassy slope, and the report of the actual diggers
remains the only evidence till the soil is cut
open again in the same way. I saw myself, at
Olympia, important lines disappearing in this way.
Dr. Purgold showed me where the line marking the
embankment of the stadium—it was never surrounded
with any stone seats—was rapidly becoming
effaced, and where the plan of the foundations
was being covered with shrubs and grass. The
day for visiting and verifying the Trojan excavations
is almost gone by. That of all the excavations
will pass away, if they are not carefully kept clear
by some permanent superintendence; and to expect
this of the Greek nation, who know they have endless
more treasures to find in new places, is more
than could reasonably be expected. The proper
safeguard is to do what Dr. Schliemann does, to
have with him not only the Greek ephoros or superintendent—generally
a very competent scholar, and
sometimes not a very friendly witness of foreign
triumphs—but also a first-rate architect, whose joint
observation will correct any hastiness or misprision,
<pb n='xiv'/><anchor id='Pgxiv'/>and so in the mouth of two or more witnesses every
word will be confirmed.
</p>

<p>
In passing on I cannot but remark how strange
it is that among the many rich men in the world
who profess an interest in archæology, not one can
be found to take up the work as Dr. Schliemann did,
to enrich science with splendid fields of new evidence,
and illustrate art, not only with the naïve efforts of
its infancy, but with forgotten models of perfect and
peerless form.
</p>

<milestone unit="tb"/>

<p>
This New Edition is framed with a view of still
satisfying the demand for the book as a traveller’s
handbook, somewhat less didactic than the official
guide-books, somewhat also, I hope, more picturesque.
For that purpose I have added a new chapter
on mediæval Greece, as well as many paragraphs
with new information, especially the ride over
Mount Erymanthus, <ref target="Pg343">pp. 343</ref>, <hi rend='italic'>sqq.</hi> I have corrected
many statements which are now antiquated by recent
discoveries, and I have obliterated the traces of
controversy borne by the Second Edition. For the
criticisms on the book are dead, while the book survives.
To me it is very pleasant to know that
many visitors to Greece have found it an agreeable
companion.
</p>

<dateline rend="text-align: left"><name><hi rend='smallcaps'>Trinity College, Dublin</hi></name>,<lb/>
<date><hi rend='italic'>February, 1892</hi></date>.</dateline>

</div><div rend="page-break-before: always">
<pb n='xv'/><anchor id='Pgxv'/>
<index index="toc" level1="Contents"/><index index="pdf" level1="Contents"/>
<head>CONTENTS.</head>
    <pgIf output="pdf">
        <then><divGen type="toc"/></then>
        <else><table rend="tblcolumns:'r lw(55) r'; latexcolumns:'rp{5cm}r'">
        <row>
            <cell rend="right"><hi rend="small">CHAP.</hi></cell>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><hi rend="small">PAGE</hi></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">I.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Introduction—First Impressions of the Coast</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg001">1</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">II.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>General Impressions of Athens and Attica</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg030">30</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">III.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Athens—The Museums—The Tombs</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg055">55</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">IV.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>The Acropolis of Athens</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg089">89</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">V.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Athens—The Theatre of Dionysus—The Areopagus</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg122">122</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">VI.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Excursions in Attica—Colonus—The Harbors—Laurium—Sunium</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg152">152</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">VII.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Excursions in Attica—Pentelicus—Marathon—Daphne—Eleusis</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg184">184</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">VIII.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>From Athens To Thebes—The Passes of Parnes and of Cithæron, Eleutheræ, Platæa</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg215">215</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">IX.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>The Plain of Orchomenus, Livadia, Chæronea</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg248">248</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">X.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Arachova—Delphi—The Bay of Kirrha</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg274">274</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">XI.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Elis—Olympia and Its Games—The Valley of the Alpheus—Mount Erymanthus—Patras</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg299">299</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">XII.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Arcadia—Andritzena—Bassæ—Megalopolis—Tripolitza</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg351">351</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <pb n='xvi'/><anchor id='Pgxvi'/>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">XIII.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Corinth—Tiryns—Argos—Nauplia—Hydra—Ægina—Epidaurus</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg388">388</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">XIV.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Kynuria—Sparta—Messene</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg435">435</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">XV.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Mycenæ and Tiryns</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg456">456</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right">XVI.</cell>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Mediæval Greece</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg492">492</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right"> </cell>
            <cell> </cell>
            <cell rend="right"> </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell rend="right"></cell>
            <cell>INDEX</cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="Pg531">531</ref></cell>
        </row>
    </table></else>
    </pgIf>
    
</div><div rend="page-break-before: always">
<pb n='xvii'/><anchor id='Pgxvii'/>
<index index="toc" level1="List of Illustrations"/><index index="pdf" level1="List of Illustrations"/>
<head>LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS.</head>

<p rend="text-align: center">
<hi rend="font-size: small">Photogravures by <hi rend='smallcaps'>A. W. Elson &amp; Co.</hi></hi>
</p>
    <pgIf output="pdf">
        <then><divGen type="fig"/></then>
        <else><table rend="tblcolumns:'lw(50m) r';latexcolumns:'p{5cm}r'">
        <row>
            <cell></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><hi rend="small">PAGE</hi></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>The Acropolis, Athens</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><hi rend='italic'><ref target="frontis">Frontispiece</ref></hi></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Along the Coast from the Throne of Xerxes</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill030">30</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>The Erechtheum from the West, Athens</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill036">36</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>A Tomb from the Via Sacra, Athens</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill078">78</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Part of the West Frieze of the Parthenon, Athens</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill110">110</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Theatre of Dionysus, Athens</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill122">122</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Mars’ Hill, Athens</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill140">140</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>The Peiræus</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill160">160</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Laurium</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill168">168</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Mount Lycabettus, Athens</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill188">188</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Looking Toward the Sea from the Soros, Marathon</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill198">198</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Salamis, from across the Bay</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill206">206</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Temple of Mysteries, Eleusis</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill212">212</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>A Greek Shepherd, Olympia</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill274">274</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <pb n='xviii'/><anchor id='Pgxviii'/>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>The Temple of Apollo, Delphi</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill284">284</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>The Banks of the Kladeus</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill302">302</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Statue of Niké, by Pæonius</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill306">306</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Kronion Hill, Olympia</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill318">318</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Entrance to the Stadium, Olympia</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill330">330</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>The Valley of the Alpheus</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill342">342</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>A Greek Peasant in National Costume</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill380">380</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Temple of Corinth</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill392">392</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Scene near Corinth, the Acro-Corinthus in the distance</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill395">395</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Gallery at Tiryns</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill406">406</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>The Palamedi, Nauplia</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill424">424</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Sculptured Lion, Nauplia</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill428">428</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Langada Pass</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill446">446</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Arcadian Gateway, Messene</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill452">452</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>The Argive Plain</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill458">458</ref></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><hi rend='smallcaps'>Lion Gate, Mycenæ</hi></cell>
            <cell rend="right"><ref target="ill472">472</ref></cell>
        </row>
    </table></else>
    </pgIf>
    
</div></front>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
